hey there Cory Lennox here for piano
with Corey and I'm so excited you're on
this video today because I'm going to
teach you how to play piano in the
simplest and most effective direct way
possible I've been playing piano for
over 30 years now and I graduated from
the Berkeley College of Music as a piano
principal but way more importantly I've
been teaching piano for over a decade
now so I've seen the journey that
beginners have to take to get from point
A to point B and be able to start
playing piano so in this video I want
this to be your One-Stop shop for all
the piano Basics you need to get started
we're going to cover playing we're going
to cover music theory technique a little
bit of arranging so I really encourage
you to make a commitment to yourself to
stay through this entire video it's
going to be really well-rounded and it's
going to give you everything you need to
get started and the very first thing I
want to jump in with today you might
think this is a little weird or a
strange place to start but it's actually
something to do with your mindset so
stay with me here this is so important I
wanted to put it first think of learning
piano as more about doing than about
learning and I know that might sound
crazy I mean I'm literally a piano
teacher so nobody values learning more
than I do but when you're first starting
out most of your progress is going to
come from doing rather than from trying
to learn a bunch of different ideas so
I'll give you an analogy imagine you're
talking to someone and they're bragging
about how good of a basketball player
they are and so you ask okay that's
great do you do drills do you play a lot
of games like how did you get so good
and they say oh no I I've never been on
the court but I've read like every book
about basketball that's out there you'd
be like okay that's great that you know
so much but to be a good basketball
player you have to go play basketball
and it's the same thing with piano you
could learn everything there is to know
about piano intellectually and still be
the worst piano player out there because
you haven't sit down and put the time in
so for you let's learn enough to get
started that's why you're here on this
video but then I immediately want you to
go start taking action practicing and
putting in the time that's how you learn
how to play piano and by the way if at
any point you want more Hands-On
in-depth guidance I do have a piano and
30 days course that you can check out in
the description or the pin comment but
enough about that let's finally dig in
to the good stuff and let's teach you
how to play now the reason most people
want to learn piano is to be able to
play their favorite songs well what is a
song a song is simply melody plus chords
I love boiling it down like that it
makes it so much easier and less
intimidating to know that's all we're
trying to do we're trying to usually
play Melody with the right hand and
chords with the left hand so Melody is
the part of a song that you would sing
or hum or whistle and the chords are the
emotional Bedrock underneath and we're
going to talk way more about this going
forward but before we can get into that
first we just have to make sure we're
all on the same page and we understand
the layout of the piano so this is what
I call the orientation section if you
already know the layout of the piano
meaning the different Keys the sharps
and flats feel free to skip ahead to the
next section but if you're a beginner or
even if you're just a little bit shaky
on some of it I want you to stay and
check this out with me as you can see
the piano has white keys and it has
Black Keys and The Black Keys are laid
out in groups of two and three two and
three all the way up and down the piano
the white keys are named after the
letters of the alphabet A B CDE e f g
and after G it just starts back over on
a again and I'm GNA show you how to find
those right now so obviously we want to
start with the letter A and the way you
find a is you go to the three Black Keys
and in between the second and third
Black Keys is the note
a then of course after a we would have B
and then c d e f and g then after G it
just starts back over on a b c d e f g
so that's the layout now one thing that
a lot of people do that drives me crazy
is they put stickers on the keys
whatever you do do not put stickers on
the keys because first of all you're
going to go to a piano that doesn't have
stickers on it and feel totally lost and
confused like the rug's been pulled out
from under you the other thing is it's
really not that hard to just learn the
layout of the keys right I'm going to
give you an exercise right now that I
show all of my beginner students and
they never have to worry about where the
keys are or what the names are or
anything like that ever again once they
do this and the way we do this exercise
is we start on a and we're going to use
the Black Keys to find every version of
a that we can on the piano so in other
words here's three Black Keys there's a
here's three more Black Keys here's
another a in between the second and
third three more Black Keys here's
another a and we're just going to go and
find every a that we possibly can and
then after a we would go to B and we
would try to find every B on the piano
so as we can see B is right after the
three black keys so I can really easily
see that I look for three Black Keys
there's B three Black Keys there's B all
the way up and down and I think you kind
of get it but I'll show you one more
example let's go from B to C now where
is C well it's right before the two
Black Keys okay so that's what we're
looking for two Black Keys there's C two
Black Keys there's C and we're going to
just go up and down and find all the C's
we possibly can and the reason we want
to use the Black Keys to orient
ourselves is because if we use the white
keys we're going to get lost okay what
do I mean by that well for the white
keys there's two spots that look almost
identical B to C looks almost exactly
the same as e to F in that this doesn't
have a black key in between and this
doesn't have a black key in between
either so if you're looking at the white
keys it's really easy to get mixed up
between b and c and e and f this happens
all the time instead what we want to do
is focus on The Black Keys If you focus
on The Black Keys it's basically
impossible to get it wrong because B is
after the three Black Keys whereas e
which looks similar is after the two
Black
Keys okay so it really helps keep
straight which notes are where that's
why we use these groups of Black Keys to
orient as we find our white keys now if
you're new to piano I highly encourage
you to pause the video right now and do
this action step sit down at the piano
and find every a find every B every c d
e f g go through each letter and if you
do this even just one or two or three
times you're going to feel incredibly
comfortable knowing where the keys are
on the piano so take a second and do
that right now now that hopefully you've
done that let's come back and let's talk
about The Black Keys The Black Keys are
what we call Sharps and flats so let's
start by talking about the sharps a
sharp is simply when you raise a note by
a half step I'll show you what I mean
let's say we're on a a half step on the
piano is just going to the next key you
possibly can the next closest key so
from a the next closest key would be
this black key and this would be called
a sharp because I took a and I raised it
up a half step let's do another example
let's say I'm on C
right A B C if I want to find C sharp I
simply go up a half step bam there I am
C Shar Flats on the other hand go down a
half step so that's pretty easy as well
let's say we're back on a if I want to
go to a flat I just need to go down the
closest distance I possibly can a half
step and this is a flat okay so a to a
flat let's do another example let's say
I'm on D and I want to go to d flat well
I lower it down to the next lowest key
and that's d
flat let's do one more example and say
I'm on B if I want to go to B flat I go
down a half step and that is B flat now
you might notice wait a minute this note
was also called a sharp well that's
because each black key has a sharp name
and a flat name I could think of this as
a going up or I could think of it as B
going down so it just depends what note
you're coming from right which angle
you're sort of approaching it so it's
the same note either way don't worry
about this too much we're going to talk
more about this later right when you
would call it a Shar when you would call
it B flat but for now just know each of
these has a sharp name and a flat name
now let me throw one last curveball at
you before we're done with this section
let's say I'm on
E and then I could go down to E flat
that's super easy easy I could go to
this black key but what if I want to go
to e sharp well let's see here's e up to
the next possible key which is this
white key and we usually think of this
as F but I could also call it e
sharp in other words Sharps and flats
can be white keys as well I'll give you
another example if I'm on C and I want
to go to C flat well I just lower it
down one key and there's C flat also
known as B and again don't get scared by
this we'll talk more about why we give
certain notes certain names later on but
for now just know the vast majority of
the time the white keys are going to be
called a bcde e FG and then you have the
Black Keys which have a sharp name and a
flat name now that you understand the
layout of the piano we can get into my
biggest shortcut to get you playing
piano as quickly as possible so why do I
say shortcut in quotes like that well on
piano really there's no shortcuts It's
All About Time dedication and and
practice but that said we can work
smarter and not harder so if there were
to be a shortcut this would be it it's
to start by focusing on cords now why do
I say that well there's a couple reasons
for it remember how earlier I said we
need Melody and chords to make a song
right the good news is the melody
doesn't always have to come from the
piano the melody could come from your
voice the melody could come from someone
else playing on a different instrument
and this makes playing piano so much
easier at the beginning because one of
the hardest things obviously is doing
two different things with two different
hands right Melody with the right hand
chords with the left hand however if
instead both hands are doing the same
thing which is playing a certain chord
that's so much easier than splitting up
the hands and doing all this different
stuff so if you like to sing even a tiny
bit what you can do is learn your chords
and then sing over the piano right sing
over the top of it and at first this
might seem kind of weird but if you
learn say four chords you could just
sing different songs over the top of
them and you could learn say 100 songs
just by playing four chords whereas if
you're going to do everything on the
piano you would have to learn a hundred
different Melodies to plug in with those
chords and that's a ton more work than
just opening your mouth and singing even
if you're not the best singer or you're
just by yourself right sitting at the
piano and no one else is around it's fun
to play some chords and sing over the
top of it and feel like a real musician
now if you totally hate the idea of
singing even just alone by yourself the
good news is we're not wasting any time
we still have to learn chords either way
even if down the road you want to play
The Melody with your right hand we've
got to start somewhere so why not start
with the chords let's dig in and let's
talk about the first two types of chords
you need to know and those chords are
major and minor so we're going to go to
the piano we're going to talk about how
to build these but I want to blow your
mind a little bit first people think
chords have to be so difficult and they
get so scared and to be Fair there are
tons of different chords out there but
the good news is the more advanced a
concept is the less you're probably
going to use it and the simpler
something is the more you're going to
use it and to prove it to you I actually
did a little experiment I took 30 of the
most famous songs and all kinds of
different genres from you know rock to
pop a little bit of classical and jazz
and I analyzed every chord in all of
these songs to find what percentage of
them were just major and minor because I
knew it was going to be a huge majority
but I didn't know the exact number what
I found was that
85.9% of the chords were just major or
minor and even crazier almost half of
the songs
46.7% were only major and minor chords
they didn't have any other type in the
entire song so if you can Master these
two different types of chords you're
really set to start playing a lot of
different stuff right out of the game so
let's go to the piano I hope I've sold
you on why this is important now I'm
going to show you how to make them and
let's get get into it now what do I mean
when I say chord well a chord is three
or more notes that you play at the same
time but before we can jump into that
let's really quickly talk about
intervals and this is so easy this is
just the distance between two notes for
example let's say I have a c and I go up
to the very next note that would be
called a second 1 2 if on the other hand
I count 1 2 3 C to e would be a third
okay then I could go 1 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 5
right I could go to a fifth a sixth a
seventh and so on and so on pretty
simple right I'm just looking at the
distance between two notes now that we
know about intervals we can start
talking about chords in its most basic
format a chord is a root note your
starting note a third right 1 2 3 and a
fifth 1 2 3 4 5 okay so when I put them
all together 1 3 and 5
I get a
chord and what's cool is you can take
that basic root third fifth shape and
move it around I could do the same thing
on D through third fifth I could go to F
or G or a right so I can sort of get a
lot of chords using that one simple
every other note kind of shape now what
makes a chord major and what makes it
minor let's get into that the only
difference between a major and a minor
chord is the middle note the Third third
in a major chord the third is four half
steps above the root so let's look at
that I'll show you what I mean if I
start on the root and I count 1 2 3 4 I
get what's called a major 3D okay and
that makes this a major chord if on the
other hand I only count three 1 2 3 I
get a minor chord so this would be C
minor and as you can see the only
difference was the middle
note now some people will take a
slightly different approach to teaching
this and you might resonate with this
better I personally don't like it as
much but some people will say okay think
four half steps to the thir and then
three half steps to the fifth then for
minor instead of
43 it's three and then four okay so to
me that is a little bit trickier because
it gives you more chances to mess up the
counting I would rather just think okay
you've got your fifth that's said either
way now you just count either four to
get major or three half steps to get
minor and the good news is if you start
with those fifths and then plug in the
middle note it's actually really easy
cuz fifths are almost always going to
match up right like white key to white
key or black key to Black key so I'll
show you C to G is a fifth D to a is a
fifth e to B is a fifth right just 1 2 3
4 5 there's a fifth there's a fifth so
you can see it's really intuitive it
fits fits on your hand perfectly and you
can just count it out 1 2 3 4 5 the only
place on the piano this will not work is
if you go to
B so B to F isn't actually quite a fifth
if you actually look at all the other
fifths I just showed you if you were to
break it down there' be seven half steps
however when I go to B to F this part of
the piano doesn't have a black key here
and this part doesn't have a black key
here so it throws off the spacing this
isn't quite seven half steps like I want
it to be it's only 1 2 3 4 5 6 right CU
I'm at this very specific point in the
piano so what I have to do to get a
fifth is raise f up to FP this is the
one place where the fifth is kind of
wonky okay same thing for The Black Keys
C Shar to G sharp is a fifth E flat to B
flat is a fifth and so on and so on the
one place that's different is again B
flat it's always the B that's it's kind
of the problem child right I want to go
from B flat to F so that's my fifth in
this case that's seven half steps so
here's the way to think about it fifths
are really easy to find it's just white
key to white key or black key to Black
key right it's just going to match up
the only place where that's different on
the entire piano is on B and B flat so
now we understand how to get the outer
notes of our chord the root and the
fifth and we understand how to very
easily get the middle note of our chord
by counting four half steps for major
and three half steps for minor so let's
apply this a little bit I think you're
going to catch on pretty quickly and
then I'm going to give you an action
step to apply this yourself so let's uh
take let's say we go to
D and we do this every other note kind
of shape now is this D major or is it D
Minor well let's count I've got my root
and I'm going to count 1 2 3 to F so
remember three three was minor making
this chord D Minor if I wanted D major I
would have to count four 1 2 3 4 so D
major would have an FP in the
middle okay so that time I just played a
random chord and analyzed it after the
fact but let's take another approach
let's say I want to intentionally find a
chord let's say I've Googled the chords
to a song and I see G minor well let's
go to G and get our fifth 1 2 3 3 4 5
then minor remembers three half steps so
all I have to do is go 1 2 3 there it is
G minor on the other hand G major as you
know we could just lift this middle note
up 1 2 3 four half steps is Major and
let's do maybe one more example starting
on a black key let's say I'm trying to
play E flat minor okay so we're really
jumping into the deep end usually you're
practicing for months or maybe even
years before before you dive into all
this chord stuff but I think you can
handle it okay so E flat minor let's say
we're trying to find that so the first
thing I need is my fifth E flat to B
flat and again you could either think of
this as seven half steps or you could
just think black e to Black key or you
could even think e and B is a fifth so
if I lower it down that's a fifth too
right however you want to think about it
then we're going to get the middle note
and minor is three half steps so I'll
count 1 2 3 and there's E flat minor so
I know that last one was a little bit
trickier but really this is all there is
to it and I want you to be prepared for
any type of major or minor chord you
come across whether it be a white key or
a black key and the way these chords are
written if you're going to Google it or
use sheet music whatever you're going to
do the way we write a major chord is we
just write the letter so C major is just
written as c e major is written as E A
minor chord however is going to have a
little M next to it so F minor would be
f with the little M next to it and this
is going to tie into some of the other
stuff we talk about later the way we're
going to get better at this and make it
second nature for us is to practice it
so let's talk about your action steps
the first thing I want you to do is take
every white key and make a major chord
and a minor chord on each one so for
example find C major then find C
minor okay then go to D let's find D
major and then d D Minor right you're
going to go through each one and take as
much time as you need and lock down
those major and minor chords then the
second action step is to do the same
thing on the Black Keys only do this
once you've done all the white keys but
then you'll go back to say C Shar and
you'll find C Shar major C Shar
minor and then you could go to E flat or
D Shar however you want to think about
it and do major and then do
minor this will take take some time as I
mentioned but it's so worth it because
again 85% of the chords you're probably
going to encounter are going to be major
or minor so you've really got to get
these down all right let's keep going so
now that we've talked major and minor
let's talk about how to actually learn
songs right we're going to actually play
songs you care about and enjoy and again
this takes so long to get to in most
piano methods but now that you've worked
on this we can actually use this to our
advantage and Leverage that knowledge so
what I would recommend doing is Googling
chords to whatever songs you want to
play and then either humming over them
or singing over them whatever it is so
for example let's say I want to play I
don't know Castle on the hill by Ed
Sheeran I'm going to see
D I'm going to see
G I'm going to see B minor which we
worked
on and then I'm going to see
a and again if you've practiced these a
little bit this is the easiest thing in
the world but it does take a little work
so then you could go through and you
could just I'm on my way driving at 90
down those country lanes right doesn't
really matter you don't have to be a
great singer but then you're playing
piano right and you could use the right
hand to play the chords or you could use
the left hand I'm going to show you
later on how to kind of use both but
just to show you that's where I think
you should start work on these chords
Google a few songs get your feet wet get
excited show yourself that you can do
this now what do you do when you come
across a chord that isn't major or minor
okay most of the other types of chords
you're going to see that aren't major or
minor that other whatever it is
15% a huge majority of that are going to
be what we call seventh chords and the
cool thing is you can actually simplify
these down to major or minor without
losing too much information so seventh
Chords it's a bit outside the scope of
this video it's not too crazy but there
is a lot more for us to get to so what I
would recommend is if you see a seven
just ignore it right if you see C7 just
play a C chord instead if you see F
minor 7 just play F minor instead it's
going to sound almost exactly the same
maybe a little bit less cool a little
bit less flavorful but it's still going
to get the idea of the song across and
just to prove to that you really don't
lose that much by simplifying the chords
let me play You Have Yourself a Merry
Little Christmas first with seventh
chords and then simplify down to major
and minor so here's seventh chords
first and now here is simplified
[Music]
down still sounds great right it's maybe
not quite as flavorful but that is a
perfectly good rendition of the song So
with major and minor you can play almost
everything you want to do that said
there are a few other types of chords
like diminished chords augmented
suspended this is all stuff that you can
learn about in my music theory course if
you'd like but it's outside the scope of
this video and frankly you're really not
going to come across these a ton if you
really need to you can Google you know
how do I play C augmented right and you
could look up those other chord shapes
as you go and here's our action step for
this section I want you to look up a few
songs that you'd like to play the easier
the better for for now certain genres
are a lot tougher than others so if
we're talking about top 40 if we're
talking about some of the mainstream
stuff anything like Edge sheering Taylor
Swift that kind of thing is going to be
pretty easy if you're into like
progressive metal or Jazz that's going
to be a lot tougher but for now I
encourage you to keep it easy even if
it's something a little more tasteful
like say The Beatles or maybe even Queen
you could probably get away with doing
this go and find a couple songs and play
either your left hand or the right hand
and play play the chords there's lots of
good chord resources I'll put a couple
of them on the screen right here any one
of them is going to be great at giving
you different chords for different songs
and last thing I'll say before we move
on is be patient with yourself it might
feel kind of weird it might not make
total sense you might not get it right
now that is okay people spend years
learning how to play piano and you're
already so far ahead of the curve
approaching it this way right so give
yourself that Grace try it out but don't
get discouraged
next up now that we've talked about how
to make these chords let's talk about
what we can do with them different ways
we can play them this is something where
you can sound way better than you
actually are on piano with very little
effort and let me show you what I mean
here let's say I've got a C chord well I
can play this either all at once which
is called a block chord or I can play it
one note at a time and that's called
broken okay I could also do a broken
chord like this I could do the bottom
note and then the top two so there's
different ways to play the same chord I
could play block or I could play broken
I could play low or I could play high so
one thing I want you to mess around with
right now this is going to be fun is
take any chord you want let's pick a
minor chord maybe something like E minor
okay and what I want you to do is get E
minor ready with both hands so here and
here okay I've got E minor E minor then
do a broken chord up from your left hand
to your right hand watch E minor broken
chord E minor broken chord listen to
that sounds pretty neat right then you
can get really fancy and just replace
your right hand with your left
hand and then you can take the right
hand even
higher and play another E minor up there
so I'm doing the same same chord right
just E minor over and over
here moving the left hand moving the
right hand and you can play around with
this and start sounding really
professional really fast with just one
chord I could come
down okay now obviously it does take a
little work but the idea behind it
really pretty simple and then you start
doing that on different chords what if I
go from D
minor
to E
minor and why not let's do another one
maybe a
minor and then I go to let's say C
right you could just play around with
this and come up with so many cool
things and we're going to get more into
this later on in the video this is
what's called arranging and arranging is
just simply how you're playing the song
right so it's not as much about what the
melody is or what the chords are it's
how you're doing them am I playing it
high low block broken we have all these
different choices and we're going to get
to more on that later but for now I
think it's high time that we switch
gears and talk about Melody now Melody
on the other side of the coin from
chords it isn't that it's more difficult
necessarily or anything like that but
it's more just that there aren't as many
tricks that we can use there's not as
many quick things I can show you and I
can say now you can play 100 Melodies
it's more about every song has its own
unique Melody and it's our job as a
Pianist to learn those melodies for the
songs we want to play and every song's a
little bit different so what I recommend
is figuring out a few different Melodies
just to get your feet wet and get you
playing the piano the more you do the
better you're going to get but for today
we're going to start with Piano Man by
Billy Joel this is a classic and it's
not that hard to play the vocal Melody
what I want you to do is go to what we
call C position that means I'm going to
take my first finger my thumb and I'm
going to put it on C and you could go to
middle C right here in the middle of the
piano or you could go to treble c a
little bit higher up it doesn't really
matter so let's say I'm right here from
C I'm going to put all my other fingers
out and this is called C
position now to play piano man we're
going to play g g g g f e f e c that's
the first phrase sing a
you're the Piano Man see if you can try
that
out then after that we just play c c c c
d d okay that's sing us a song
tonight the next part is e f g g g g f e
f e
c well we're all in the mood for a
Melody the very last part is c c c f e c
c now in the actual song He dips down a
little there you've got us but here
we're just going to keep it on C just to
make it easy you've got us feeling all
right okay so I know I took that pretty
fast feel free to pause any of those
phrases and go back and really look at
it but I'm going to play the whole thing
so you can hear what it sounds like sing
us a song You're The Piano Man sing us a
song
tonight well we're all in the mood for a
Melody you've got us feeling all
right it's that easy now what I don't
want you to do you might have noticed I
kept my hand here the whole time one of
the worst mistakes you can make playing
piano is just trying to use these first
three fingers now yes four and five are
weaker but we've got to use them to get
them stronger so don't cheat on this
melody by moving your hand around to
different places just keep it right
where you started and you'll be able to
reach all of the notes that's why I
picked this song all of that said see if
you can pause the video and play The
Melody to piano man let's do one more
Melody before we move on to anything
else because again you just want to play
as many Melodies as you can possibly do
to condition your right hand and start
playing piano better and better so let's
do Don't Stop Believing I love the
classic rock songs because a lot of
different Generations know them uh so
bear with me I know maybe this isn't
your thing but try this out anyway the
first phrase is going to be c e c d d e
and that's going to be she's just a
small town girl then we're going to do c
c c c g g e d okay watch that living in
a lonely
world then c e c d d e d c d e c that
one's a little bit long longer but I'm
writing it on the screen for you and
that's going to be she took the midnight
train
anywhere we're doing this a little bit
different Journey does it in a different
key but for now we're just trying to
keep this easy okay so that whole verse
just
goes then once you get that the good
news is you can just repeat it and the
second part of the verse is the same
Melody but with different lyrics right
he's just a city boy born and raised in
South Detroit he took the midnight train
going anywhere right same Melody
different words so this was just a tiny
bit to get your right hand into the
melody Zone there's so much more we
could talk about we've got a lot more to
get to in this video including using our
right hand more and more but I highly
recommend checking out my piano and 30
days course if you want to go way more
in depth on all this stuff okay now that
you've done that let's switch gears a
little bit and let's talk about the
world of technique so technique simply
means how you're using your hand to play
the keys and obviously there's proper
form and there's improper form right
just like anything else weightlifting
Sports whatever on piano we want to have
good form obviously and here's what I
want you to do we're going to test your
Technique a little bit let's play your
thumb on C and then go through every
finger from there c d e f g and you can
do the same thing with your left hand we
can play C with our Pinky and walk up to
our
thumb now let's look at what our hands
were doing as we played that the easiest
way to explain it is we always want to
have a curve to our hand almost like
you're holding a tennis ball or a bubble
and the other thing is we don't want to
let our fingers bow in as we play the
keys you can see here I'm bending at
that joint which is actually really
painful long term especially as you
start playing louder and the thing is
most people when they start playing
piano that is their default right as you
go down to hit the key all of a sudden
it pops in like that so really watch out
that you don't do this this is going to
take some serious work and I'm going to
give you my favorite technique exercise
in a second that shows you how to work
on all this but let me show you a few
more ways where people go wrong right
things you want to void so another thing
people will do is they'll flip their
hand up as they go to their pinky right
and what's Happening Here is you're
trying to use your hand to help your
pinky don't do that let your fingers do
their own work
okay another thing that people sometimes
do is they pop the bubble and they go
kind of flat for each note this is
especially an issue with a lot of
younger kids but a lot of adults do it
too where they think they have to put so
much force into the
notes right and you end end up sort of
slamming your hand down and obviously we
don't want that either so there's a lot
of ways to go wrong another thing is you
could pop out like this off to the side
but let's just talk about what do you
want to do right because if you just
focus on the right way you're going to
avoid all the wrong ways the right way
again is curve fingers don't bend at the
joints you know just keep it curved and
don't pop up or out and really it all
boils down to what I tell my students
which is just keep your hand normal
right there you go I didn't do anything
weird or crazy I just went through each
note kept my hand relaxed curved and
normal so a way you can work on this
here's the best way to practice your
Technique we're going to play each of
these fingers three times in a row very
slowly so first I'm going to do my
thumb that one's easy now we're going to
go to our pointer finger we're going to
go one 2 3 it's very slow notice I'm
focusing the reason I'm going slow is to
make sure I'm not letting this happen
and to make sure I'm not popping the
bubble okay I'm just trying to get it
exactly right then I go to my third
finger then I go to my fourth
finger and then I go to my fifth finger
and four and five are the hardest you're
going to want to spend some time making
sure your Technique is good and you
don't have to stress about this too much
or spend hours doing this it's just a
little check-in that you can do every
now and then to make sure that your
Technique is where you want it to be so
I recommend right now pause this video
and do this action step of playing each
finger three times and then if you want
to up your Technique game further this
is a lot harder so maybe don't try it
today maybe wait a week or month
whatever it is but play all five fingers
and then you go back and do the same
exercise I just showed you thumb three
times pointer finger making sure to keep
the curve third finger fourth finger and
fifth
finger that one's tough but it can
really help your Technique if you find
you're having issues with your hand
popping up or your hand going flat
fingers bending it helps with all that
so I know this isn't the most exciting
for everyone thank you for sticking with
me let's keep on going now we have to
talk about putting both hands together
this is where things get a little more
interesting because obviously our hands
are doing different things right hand is
doing Melody and left hand is doing
chords but fear not as you know I'm a
big fan of working smarter not harder so
I've got some tricks and tips for this
as well and the biggest tip I have is
we're going to use arranging to our
advantage remember I used that word
earlier arranging that means how am I
playing what I'm playing and what a lot
of people don't know is you can really
set the level of how easy or difficult
you want a song to be so let me show you
what I mean here and for this whole part
of the video don't worry about trying to
play along or follow along on the piano
I'm just GNA play for you and illustrate
different difficulty levels and how you
would control that right so let's take
the song how far I'll go from Moana this
is a Disney song and maybe the first
level is you're a brand new beginner and
all you can do is play The Melody that's
fine and maybe the second level is
you're playing the right hand and adding
in the left hand but just with single
notes not with entire chords and the way
we can do that is we can use what we
call the root of each chord and the root
is simply just the note the chord is
built off of so in other words C major
the root note is C okay for something
like uh G minor the root note would be G
right here okay so uh basically just
using single notes in the left hand
watch I could
go
now maybe the third level is I level up
that left hand to full
[Music]
chords then maybe after that I graduate
to the next level which is doing a more
steady left hand that actually has a
consistent beat to it check this
out
maybe after that I go to Broken chords
in the left hand so now instead of all
together I'm doing a broken
chord same exact chord but now I'm
playing one note at a time and kind of
doing a arpeggiation to it right so that
might
go
or as an alternate approach on the same
kind of level maybe I'll do like a slash
I could do a rhythmic left hand with the
block cords right so I could do like a I
don't even
know something like that I'd probably
have to sit and figure fig out a better
Rhythm but just top of the head that's
something you could do and now maybe the
next level is I do a more advanced right
hand so there's a couple ways I could do
that I could take from the chord and I
could add some of those notes into the
right hand as I play the melody so for
example when I play
this what if when I hit this note the
top of
that I add in G from the left hand and I
add it here on the right hand
too
okay now I'm working with the chord and
I'm adding in some chord tones and
taking that approach I could really
level up the right hand I could do
something
[Music]
like or maybe I could do what we call
octaves with the right hand so an octave
is just eight notes apart on the piano
it's an interval of an eighth in other
words 1 2 3 4 5 6 78 C to C or D to d
right it's two versions of the same note
so two C's or two G's right those are
all octaves so I could play The Melody
instead of one note at a time I could
play
octaves right so that might give
me and then the last step would be I can
do all of the above I can do different
combinations so if you hear a really
good pianist they're not just sticking
to one or the other they're not boxing
themselves in so then maybe I could do a
mix of all of the above right I could do
something like chord tones in the right
hand and broken chords in the left
[Music]
hand and then I go to
octaves and then maybe I go to like a
rhythmic left
hand and I sort of use all the tools at
my disposal to play the song with my own
particular style now of course this
takes years to get to years of work to
get to that level but I just want to
show you the basic concept that you can
set the difficulty level if all you can
do right now is the melody great if
however you get a little more
comfortable you want to add some bass
notes that's awesome if you want to
start adding chords like full-on chords
do that you could do them broken and you
just go step by step so this is where
the knowledge part of it kind of breaks
down and it's more important to do the
practicing part because you might spend
a year on each of these levels or maybe
not maybe like 3 months but it is going
to take a decent chunk of time to go
through those different levels and get
comfortable with each one and every song
is different so some songs might be
really easy to match the right and the
left others might be tougher and you
have to take a simpler approach coming
up with an action step for this section
was actually really difficult because
there's so many different levels of
arranging there's different levels of
skill that you could be at and every
song is going to feel different in the
way it interacts with Melody and chords
but one thing we can do is just a simple
hand syncing exercise and we'll do an
easy version and then a slightly harder
version so the easy version is we're
going to do a C5 tone
scale so I'm just walking from C up to
my pinky and back down then with your
left hand you're going to play a C
chord and the way we're going to sync it
up is we're going to play at the bottom
of the scale and we're we're going to
play at the top of the scale watch
[Music]
this there you have it so that's pretty
easy but it it'll just give you a taste
of sinking those hands together now a
slightly harder version is we can do a
broken chord with our left
[Music]
hand and the same right hand that we
just did and the Saving Grace here what
makes it kind of easy is we are going to
match our notes we're going to match on
C
then we're going to match on
E then G then e then match on C's so
watch that again match match match match
match so for your action step try one of
those versions either block or broken
and then as a more long-term action step
I want you to go learn as many songs as
you can right so learn different
Melodies look up the chords try to piece
them together and sort of get in the
trenches and try out so this is where
just a YouTube video kind of falls short
obviously we can't do 3 years of piano
lessons in one video you need a
long-term plan either a course or a
lesson book or taking private lessons
with the teacher that is where a lot of
your progress is going to come from but
that said there's still a ton more to
talk about in this video so let's keep
on going okay so now that you probably
feel like completely overwhelmed and
just hit with so much information let's
take a breather and let's talk about
okay we we have have all these different
ideas in our head we know we need to
practice whether it be just melody or
Melody with some easy chords whatever
level you're ready for we need to talk
about how to learn songs right how do
you actually go out and start practicing
music well there's a lot of different
ways you can learn a song thankfully so
you have to find the way that works for
you one of the most popular ways is of
course reading sheet music that's what
most people think of right sitting down
with the piece of music and reading it
now this I'm a little bit conflicted
about I think it's so important to be
able to read obviously I teach all my
students it's like the main thing we
work on right for the first however many
years right um but when you're first
starting out it can be a very slow
process it takes a long time to be able
to read realize what you're reading sync
it up with the hands put it all together
it just takes some serious time but if
you do want to learn more about reading
I do have a quick crash course video on
that that I'll put in the description as
well but what if you don't want to
dedicate that time yet or you're not
sure and you want to find a different
way to learn songs just at the beginning
well another way you can learn songs is
here on YouTube right you can look up
YouTube tutorials and find people
showing you with overhead videos how to
play the songs you want to play so those
can be really easy they walk you through
every step and of course you'll have to
pick songs that are at your skill level
but I do think that's a good way to just
jump in and sort of get started now
another way to learn songs is to use
what we call lead sheets so a lead sheet
does require a little bit of reading but
what it is is it it's a Melody with a
chord symbol so this is a simplified way
of reading I loved this when I started
piano um because I hated site reading
and I was actually quite bad at it so
what this does is you're just reading
the melody and you're plugging in the
chords on the left hand based on the
chord symbols like we talked about and
it basically just frees up your mental
energy from having to read two lines to
you're reading one line and the left
hand you're just kind of plugging in
those chords like I said so that's
something you can look into but let's go
to the last way
and this is the way that I think a lot
of people would prefer to do it but it's
also the most advanced which is playing
by ear because you want to have some
piano skills before you try to play by
ear in other words when you go to play
by ear let's say you could hear every
single note in a song Perfectly if your
hands aren't trained you won't be able
to play it right so the ear training is
always going to be limited by your
playing ability of course you can still
play around and try to figure out some
Melodies on your own but as a long-term
strategy I think you need to start with
one of the other ones and then worry
about training your ear a little bit
later moving on to the next part of the
video we're going to talk about probably
my favorite thing to teach and I waited
so long to get to this because this is
the kind of stuff I normally talk about
on my channel so you might have seen
this before but we're going to talk
about music theory and this is so
important this is what I call the
language of Music in other words it
helps you just sort of understand why
you're doing what you're doing and this
is huge whether you want to write songs
improvise or read sheet music played by
ear you're going to need to understand
the language of music okay this is what
ties all those skills together so people
who don't learn this always find music
inscrutable and complicated and
confusing whereas the people who do
learn it understand so much better and
things come so much easier when they're
trying to set out to do those things
that said let's go back to the piano and
let's talk now the first thing to jump
in with is talking about scales and I
know that doesn't sound exciting but I
think a lot of lot of people teach this
kind of backwards I'm not going to show
you how to make them yet first I want to
show you why we even care about them
right why do we care about scales what
are they used for and the reason we care
about scales is remember earlier I said
all songs boil down to melody plus
chords well guess what Melody comes from
scales and believe it or not our chords
come from scales as well so both halves
of that equation come from scales Melody
and chords and we'll start here with
melodies most people think of scales in
the context of creating or playing
Melodies which is totally fair that's a
huge way that we use them for example
let's say I play 1 2 3 5 in my scale and
I'll show you how to make these in a
second but if I just play 1 2 3 five all
of a sudden I'm playing Beyonce If I
Were a Boy I'm playing the greatest
showman never enough I'm playing a
Christian worship song I Could Sing of
Your Love it's all from that 1 2 3 5
pattern let me give you another example
let's say I just play straight down
through a C
[Music]
scale it doesn't really sound like
anything yet but what if I put a little
bit of Rhythm to it check this
[Music]
out all of a sudden it becomes Joy to
the World and all that song is doing at
the beginning is walking down through
the scale note by note here's an even
easier example what if I just play 1 2 3
4 5
and then 5 43 2
1 that's Beauty and the Beast Bitter
Sweet and strange finding you can change
so that is how people make Melodies
pretty cool right you're just taking
certain patterns of notes from the scale
now I also mentioned that scales can
help you with ear training so one thing
I see all the time is people are trying
to figure out a song but they don't know
their scales and it makes it way harder
than it has to be for example let's say
I'm trying to figure out Fireflies by
Owl City and I know the general Melodies
like I'd like to I'd like to make make
myself believe oh man so that's really
tough right well it's only tough because
I'm not using a scale what I need to do
instead is take a step back and learn my
scales and it's going to be a 100 times
easier check this out there I go now
that I have a scale this is going to be
so much easier now I can just go I'd
like to make
myself and there I go I'm on the right
keys and as for improvisation or
songwriting if I know my scale anything
within a scale is at least going to
sound decent this is a great jumping off
point for making something
up or writing a
song right whatever it is I'm sort of
just staying within my scale and I can't
go wrong so now the question is well
wait Cory how did you do this how did
you make a scale and now I'll be more
than happy to show you now that you
actually want to learn how to do it but
I did didn't want to show you until you
actually cared enough to learn how we
make these the way we make a scale is
with something I call the golden scale
formula and it looks like this whole
step whole step half step whole step
whole step whole step half step so we
already covered half steps in the
orientation section that is where you go
from one key to the very next whether
it's white or black right it's the
closest distance you can go that's a
half step a whole step is just two half
steps so for example
a up a whole step would be 1 2 then B up
a whole step would be 1
2 and so on one two that's a whole step
one two that's a whole step so I
encourage you if that's totally foreign
to you maybe take a second and try a all
half step scale which we call the
chromatic
scale and there's a more like technical
way to play it but for now just use your
pointer
finger and then once you've done the
half steps once once you've practiced
those you can come back and work with
the whole steps right so doing something
like this c d e whole step whole step
and so on just figure out how to do all
whole steps as well so once you've
practiced your half steps and your whole
steps now we're ready to talk about
combining them to make an actual scale
and we call this the major scale by the
way and all I'm going to do is like I
showed you start on a note any note you
want in this case let's start easy with
c
then I'm just going to follow the golden
scale formula so C up a whole step up a
whole step half step whole step whole
step whole step half step and what you
saw right there was that the C scale is
all white keys
right now when you're first figuring out
your scales I recommend using your
pointer finger so this might drive some
piano teachers crazy there's a
technically correct way to play each
scale but I don't want you to try to do
two things at once right people try and
do their fingers and they try to do
these Crossovers and stuff before they
really know what their scale even is yet
and they just get jumbled so I want to
take that out of the equation just use
one finger keep it simple we can always
go back and find the right fingers later
for now you're focused on getting the
right notes let's do another example
let's go to the G scale so if I want to
make a G scale I'll start on G then then
I go up a whole step whole step half
step whole step whole step whole step
one two and half step so you saw the G
scale actually has a sharp in
it it has F sharp now after you finish a
scale you want to take stock of what you
just did we don't want to have to always
go back and say whole step whole step
half step no we want to try to start
memorizing these so I'm going to
mentally make a note or or maybe you
could even write it down but I'm going
to think the G scale has one sharp which
is f
Shar okay I'm going to take stock of
that let's do one more example and then
I'm going to show you something else
right let's go to say an f scale so if
we start on F we can go whole step whole
step half step whole step whole step
whole step half step now this scale had
one black key as
well and remember back in the
orientation section I told you we'd talk
more about why we would name certain
notes sharp and why we would name
certain notes flat in other words when I
play this scale and I have this
note is this a sharp or is it B flat
it's a good question right well here's
the answer we always want to keep the
alphabet in order right so I don't want
to say like a a c d no I just want to
say a b c d right so if I look at my my
scale f g a b b flat C so in this case
it's going to be B flat so I can say FG
a b c as opposed to if I tried to say a
sharp it would be f g a a c not quite
right so this is what determines if
we're in say a Sharp key or a flat key
it's really easy you just want to keep
that alphabet in order and the biggest
mistake people make with scales is they
say Okay whole step whole step half step
now wait a minute I've already gone
wrong so what's the problem well if I
play my first note and say whole step I
actually haven't stepped anywhere right
I've just got one note so instead I need
to say starting note and then I can
start stepping from there whole step
whole step half step and so on now
different songs are going to use
different scales right some songs might
use a d
scale and other songs s might use a e
scale so it's just up to the songwriter
it's up to the vocalist right how high
or low do you want to sing what sort of
scales do you like there's so many
factors that go into the Songwriter's
choices but for our end as a Pianist we
have to sort of be ready to play in
these different keys right so what I
recommend doing here's your action step
I want you to take the golden scale
formula and figure out every white key
scale so I'm talking about about the C
scale d e f g a b and then you're back
to C okay once you've done that if you
feel like you really got it maybe even
spend a month just doing the white key
scales then you can come back and try
the black key scales and they're
formulated the exact same way but they
just start on a black key instead of a
white key so let's quickly do an example
of a black key scale and then I'll let
you pause the video into your action
step so let's say we're trying to play a
flat okay so again we're going to go
whole
step whole step half step whole step
whole step whole step half step no
different at all I just started on a
black key so take a moment now pause the
video and try the action step do all of
the white key scales and then later on
maybe a week a month later try the black
key scales as well once you're back I
want to talk really quickly before we
move on about technique so some people
get really into scales as a technique
exercise right they put on a metronome
they drill the scales and four octaves
and they're doing all kinds of different
stuff right to me when you're a beginner
you're not going to get as much mileage
out of that as you think I think there
are way better ways you could spend your
time so I don't recommend drilling the
scales as a technical exercise yet you
can later on but what I'm going to do is
at the very least show you the correct
fingers to use typically for most of the
white key scales we're going to want
want to do what's called a cross under
on the finger three okay so what does
that mean let's say I'm doing my C scale
what I want to do is instead of just
going 1 2 3 4 5 and then running out of
fingers right instead I want to cross
under three in other words 1 2 3 cross
my thumb under and then keep
going now on the way back down I just do
the
opposite I'm going to cross my third
finger
over and I've got exactly enough fingers
to make it through the scale left hand
is the same deal but going the other way
cuz your left hand's obviously facing
the opposite direction so I'm going to
go from five all the way up to one cross
to
three then I'm going to come back down
and cross under three on the way
down and the really good news is almost
every white key scale works that same
way if I'm playing say a G scale I'm
going to cross under
three if I'm playing an e scale I'm
going to cross to three
right same fingers that I've been doing
the only two places where we don't use
three as our cross under point is the f
scale for the right hand because check
this out I've got this B flat so it' be
really weird to like do that right so
instead I'm going to go to my fourth
finger 1 2 3 4 cross under and end on
four at the top okay so that's my f
scale
and then when I come down I cross to
four to get back down for the left hand
you can do the f scale the way you've
always done right with a three
crossover because the flat sits on a
different point on your left hand than
it does on the right this is totally
comfortable but for the left hand the
left hand one that's different is the B
scale I want to start not on my pinky
like I normally would but on my fourth
finger
here and that just allows me to play the
scale more comfortably instead of like
my thumb ending up on Black Keys or
anything like that and honestly I really
don't want you to stress about this to
me playing and drilling the scales isn't
as important as just knowing them so
even if you just chicken peck it but you
know exactly where an a major scale is
that is going to serve you very well
then later on you can come back and
maybe try using the right
fingers but for now don't let it stress
you out now I know this video has been a
lot so far but this is one of my
favorite things to get to so stay with
me here you might be asking well Cory I
I get how Melodies and scales kind of
work together but didn't you also say
chords come from scales too and the
answer is yes yes I did chords actually
can come from our scale as well and we
call these dionic chords in other words
chords that come from a scale just like
we're saying so let me show you exactly
what I mean let's take a C scale for
instance all white keys well what I can
do is start on the first note of the C
scale which is C and I can build a chord
off that first
note remember root 3D fth so there we go
now because it's based off the first
note of the scale I call it the one
chord easy enough if I go to the second
note of the scale I'm going to call that
chord A two chord if I go to the third
note I'll call it a three chord and four
five 6 7 and so on and those are all the
quote unquote correct chords in the key
of C so if I'm trying to write a song in
the key of C or play somebody else's
song improvise ear train whatever it is
that's going to be my pallet of colors
to work with for the ccale all of those
chords and what's cool is did you have
to worry about whether they were major
or minor or diminished or no no we
didn't the scale automatically gave us
the right chords in that key
unfortunately it's not always going to
be that easy the C scale is all white
key so that's pretty simple but let's
pick a different scale let's say we have
a G
scale as I go through and I start
finding my chords in the key of G I have
to remember that I have an fshp so
here's my one chord starting on the
first note of the scale that's G then
the two chord on the second note of the
scale is a minor the three chord watch
this I don't want to play F I want to
play F sharp so in other words almost
don't even think of this note as
existing in the Q of G right we have FP
not F natural so then from my three
chord to my four chord my five chord
again I'm going to have FP my six Chord
my seven chord and my one chord so those
would be the correct chords in the key
of G and what I really love about this
is it pairs down the scary world of
chords because there's literally
hundreds if not thousands of chords out
there and yet if I stick with this
format at any given moment I know what
all the right chords are going to be and
I put that in air quotes I should
probably give my disclaimer I always
give which is that in music there really
are no rules there's just jumping off
points so you could totally break the
rules plenty of composers and
songwriters do but you want to start
with the basics before you worry about
breaking the rules so there's plenty of
times in the key of G where you might
use an F natural but that's not the
default starting place right so I hope
that makes sense it's kind of like in
painting
you could be Picasso and put two eyes on
the same side of someone's face but
usually that's not how you would paint a
human face right and you kind of have to
learn the basics first before you get
into the crazy stuff your action step
for this section is to pick any white
key scale and find the dionic cords
within that scale so I'll put them on
the screen in the order of the easiest
to the hardest to do and really this
comes down to the number of Sharps so
obviously C is the easiest because
there's no sharps or flat
then G and F are the next most difficult
with only one sharp and one flat
respectively and then you kind of go on
from there D has two sharps a has three
and so on and let's say you pick the D
scale well that scale has two sharps I
have to think about as I go through and
you'll know this if you did your action
step for the scale section and the two
sharps it has are F and C Shar so as I
go through I just got to remember F and
C Shar as I find my one Chord my two 3 4
4 5 6 7 and back to one there you go and
you could maybe even try one a day or
one a week whatever it is but spend some
time with this because this really does
pay off and now that we understand
dionic chords in other words pulling
those chords out of a scale now we can
go on to another one of my favorite
topics which is chord progressions so
what is a chord progression well it's
simply a set pattern of chords that you
use to create your song so for example I
could play one to four right that could
be my entire song it's just going back
between one and
four okay and there are plenty of songs
that do that just off the top of my head
we've got bad by You2 1979 by the
Smashing Pumpkins and State of Grace by
Taylor Swift now each of those songs
does have like a couple other chords
that it goes to at a certain point or
another but the vast majority of those
songs are just one to four but by far in
a way the most famous chord progression
is one that I call the legendary chord
progression because I just love being
over the top about it but it's 1 5 6 and
four and it sounds like this in the KFC
I would go
1 5 6
4 okay so sounds simple enough but I
could play literally hundreds of songs
with that chord progression I can play
everything from like 80s hits like
forever
young to uh the Moana song we did
earlier from
[Music]
Disney I could do the
office I could do Maroon
Five and I kid you not I could just sit
here for so long and play song after
song after song that just uses that
progression and I've got to admit it's
pretty awesome how much mileage you can
get out of just say four chords now the
one kind of complicating factor is not
all of those songs are in the same key
in other words they're not all using the
C scale the office for example uses the
G
scale the Moana one that uses the E
scale
okay so different songs will use
different scales but here's the good
news even though different songs use
different scales if you don't have
perfect pitch which I don't our ear
doesn't care a ton about what particular
scale of song is using for example when
I played the office in the key of
C were you like wait what song is that
right I have no idea what that is or
earlier I did Beauty and the Beast in
the wrong key you know it's not normally
in the key ofc which is where I played
[Music]
it but yet you're not sitting there like
wait a minute what song is that right
like you know what song it is because
your ear is perfectly happy to hear
Beauty and the Beast in the key of
[Music]
C or to hear it in the key of C sharp
which is where the original
is right so in this way not having
Perfect Pitch can really be a blessing
and this is what singers do all the time
if a song is too high or too low or if
you're transposing it from male to
female whatever it is um you can
transpose or shift the scale that a song
is using and maybe that's a little bit
outside the scope of this video but the
idea is you take the same chord
progression in this case 1 5 6 4 and you
map it to a different scale you take the
melody right Beauty and the Beast 1 2 3
4 5 and you map that to a different
scale and we call that transposing so
maybe a little bit outside the scope of
this video but I just want to show you
how much you can do with these different
ideas learning your scales learning your
different chords this is what playing
piano is so the more time you spend
playing around with this stuff the
better you're going to get so let's say
you've got a low voice like maybe you're
a bass and you just want to rock Let It
Go in the key of C let it go let it go
can't hold it back anymore no one's
going to come up and be like actually
that's in the key of A flat major or F
minor like no no one no one cares it
sounds like the song you're playing the
right chords just in a different scale
your action step for this section is to
play around with different chord
progressions so let's say we pick 1 3 6
4 one of my favorites first thing I've
got to do is figure out what key I want
to play in and let's say we want to play
in the key of A so this ties back into
the dionic chords right so if I did my a
chords then I've got those ready to go
and I can just pick a certain order so
like I said I'm going to do one and then
1 2 3 I'm going to do the three
chord then 3 4 5 6 would be F Shar
minor and then four
654 would be D so all together I have
3 6 and four so that could be a song
right there right starting on 1 to 3 to
6 to 4
so as you can see each of the things
that we talked about really Builds on
the last right if you haven't done your
scales if you haven't done your dionic
cords then doing chord progressions like
that that's going to be really tough so
make sure you've done the action steps
put in the time and let's keep on going
moving on now I want to cover one more
thing with chords and one more thing
with scales I outlined this whole video
before I started and I realized that I
really wanted to get these last two
things in here because I think they are
essential Concepts and I hope you're
still with me if you need to pause the
video and come back later I totally get
it but let's talk about one more thing
with the chords which are called
inversions this is really easy I promise
you all an inversion is is changing the
order of the notes within a chord for
example I know a c chord is c e and G
now what I could do is take C from the
bottom and move it to the
top okay now I've got what we call a
first inversion c
chord it's still c e g but I just
changed the order now I could invert it
up again I could move e to the top and I
have second inversion which is g c and e
then if I invert it one more time I get
back to root position which has C on
bottom you don't have to stress about
this a ton honestly I really like root
position chords where I just keep
everything in
order but one place where doing
inversion really can help especially as
a beginner is it can make it easier to
get from one chord to another for
example let's say I want to go from C to
F okay this is kind of a big
jump so as I'm playing maybe I have a
Melody up here jumping that left hand
it's not the hardest thing in the world
but maybe it could be easier so I might
notice okay both the C chord and the F
chord both have the note C within them
okay for the F chord it's the top note
for the C chord it's the starting note
the bottom note so what if I do an
inverted F chord in other words instead
of f a c i put it in a different order
like c f and a so I just move these two
up
here now I get to keep C the same and
switch between those two chords so much
easier pretty cool right right now it
just depends on what chords you're
switching between sometimes there's an
easy way to do the switch and other
times you just kind of have to jump to a
different chord more times than not you
can find a way to finesse your way into
a different chord I'll give you one more
example if I want to go from C major to
a
minor you'll actually notice those
chords have two notes in common c and e
for the c major and c and e as well for
the a minor so what I can do check this
out I'm just going to change C major to
a minor playing the same notes I was a c
and e but just in a different order so I
took a c e from here then I moved it
down and did a c e there now my switch
is super easy it's just one
note so it's just something to be aware
of that you can do this for some
beginners it really stresses them out
and they hate the idea of these
inversions and it's confusing using and
they don't get switch in the order so if
that's you don't worry about it come
back to this video later work with the
root position cords first and then you
can focus on Switching up the order if
you want to later on now moving on from
our inversions let's cover the last
Chunk in our music theory section here
which is minor scales and I'm including
this because I get a lot of complaints
that I don't talk enough about them in
my videos and the reason I don't is
because to me it's just so simple that
it kind of naturally flows out of
everything we've already done so first
thing to talk about though is what even
is a major key or a minor key well very
simply a major key has a more happy
sound and a minor key has a more sad
kind of depressed sound maybe something
like
this right that's a little bit darker
but the good news is every major scale
already has a minor scale built into it
so now you're probably thinking dude
what I'll show you if you go to the
sixth note of a major scale and you just
play 6 to 6 that is what's called the
relative minor for example the C scale
we talked about was all white keys
right now if I go to the sixth note of
that scale 1 2 3 4 56 I get a now I'm
going to play from a to a using again
all y Keys same as the C
scale right just to show you that is the
a minor
scale super easy let me show you another
example let's say I'm looking at the f
scale so I could play from F to
F or I could go to the relative minor
which starts again on the sixth note so
let's count one 2 3 4 5 6 that puts me
on D so if I want to play in this case D
Minor all I have to do now is play from
D to D while keeping this same scale
check it
out
and there's D Minor so if you want a
darker sound if you like the minor key
stuff just remember go to the sixth note
of a major scale and you get your minor
key scale now there's plenty more we
could talk about with minor keys but I
don't want this to just become a music
theory video I've already got a lot of
Music Theory stuff on my channel so you
can watch another video after this one
to get more into it but for now let's
give ourselves a break and let's go back
to the music room for the last section
we're definitely at the last section of
the video here so if you've made it to
this point you are a champion thank you
so much for staying with me and I hope
you've loved it so far now this last
section is going to be miscellaneous
things right we're going to talk about
posos lesson books gear just a mish mash
of things that I think we should cover
before I wrap up this video and let's
start with the piano itself now
obviously the top tier is a real piano
an acoustic piano whether that be a
grand or an upright or whatever else you
might have that's definitely going to be
the best option you're going to have
weight to the keys you're going to have
overtones and richness from the real
strings and the body of the piano but if
you don't have a real piano there are
definitely some affordable options for
keyboards now a couple things you want
to look for I only have two criteria you
want to make sure the keyboard is full
size which means 88 keys and you might
be tempted to skimp on it at the
beginning because it's cheaper to get
less keys but you're going to grow out
of that so fast so I recommend just bite
the bullet a little bit and get the full
size keyboard and you're going to thank
yourself down the road the other thing
is you want weighted keys and it could
be semi- weighted it could be fully
weighted but you want some kind of
weight to it and I've even seen like
these full sort of like faux piano
modules where the keys are just plastic
and it feels terrible to play and this
happened to me it can throw you off when
you go play a real piano so when I went
to audition for Berkeley I had come from
these plastic keys and then I went to a
real piano and like none of my notes
came out on the real thing so it was
such a train wreck but I'm here to stop
that happening to you so make sure you
get those weighted keys and what I'll do
is I'll actually put a few options for
different keyboards in the description
of this video so you can check out
different price points and if you are in
the market for a real piano I would
highly recommend Facebook Marketplace
whenever people are moving or you know
changing things up switching houses
they're always trying to get rid of
pianos because they're so heavy and you
typically have to pay movers to move
them so if you offer to cover the cost
of movers typically they'll give the
piano to you for a huge discount right
if not free but the downside is you have
to make sure that the piano is tuned and
it can get out of tune when you move it
so you might have to hire a tuner when
it gets to you maybe take a musician
friend along to make sure it's playable
the keys aren't sticking there's nothing
weird going on with it and uh just scope
it out before you decide to purchase in
terms of programs and lesson books
obviously I highly recommend my program
which I've talked about but if you'd
rather go with a lesson book the best
one I found is the adult piano Adventure
series it looks like this and it's the
most gradual easy to follow along clear
yet impactful lesson book I've ever seen
I love it and I actually switched over
as a teacher because I grew up with
Alfred's and I found that people just
progress so much more smoothly with
piano Adventures so that's my
recommendation you can check it out in
the link below as well and I'm actually
a really big fan of using lesson books
to learn piano and I know it seems
boring I didn't love it when I was
starting out but it really does go
through everything in the most
methodical and gradual way possible so
you move from step one to step two to
step three and if you just stay with it
you're really going to be amazing by the
time you reach the end of a book or a
book series and honestly I think it's
one of the best ways to get the most out
of the time you spend practicing because
if you just sort of go it alone and you
try to teach yourself or you try to
learn just songs you like you're
probably going to like do things a
certain way you're going to develop
certain roadblocks you're going to be
limited in certain capacity
whereas the lesson books are going to
make sure you're well-rounded you're
exposed to a lot of different ideas and
you're going to be pretty much good to
go all right I'm having my daughter Viv
joined me for this part of the video it
was just Halloween so we have our little
skeleton hoodie here but yeah so
probably the most common question that
beginners ask is how long does it take
to learn piano and here's the thing I
really don't like that question because
imagine asking somebody hey uh how long
does it take to make money they'd be
like what do you mean like a dollar like
$1,000 six figures what what do you mean
right it's the same way on piano do you
mean play Mary Had a Little Lamb cuz you
could do that today do you mean you know
play pop songs cuz then maybe a year do
you mean play classical pieces that
could be yeah that could be 5 to 10
years or do you mean perfectly play the
Winter Wind Aude or lack comp Panella
with no mistakes cuz that could take you
know a life time to really perfect that
at a concert pianist level so it depends
what you want to do
that's
you you tell them it depends what you
want to do yay I would say as a general
rule of thumb about 1 to 3 years is
where you're going to start to see
progress and be reasonably comfortable
but I always say for the entire first
year don't judge yourself at all check
your ego at the door be patient and just
give yourself a chance to grow and learn
how to do it okay you've survived you've
made it to the end of the video and once
again and I'm so proud of you for
watching all the way through so let this
be the start of your new life playing
piano the start of a New Journey and get
out there and actually go apply the
action steps grab my chorus if you want
to if you want to get a little more in
depth and just start playing look up
some chords re-watch this video whatever
it is that you're most excited by just
jump in and don't overthink it I'm so
excited for you to start this journey
and develop a skill that will pay off
for life so have fun with it and piano
on